Finding Aid for the Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education Records LSC.1923
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Subject Files, 1913-2012
  - Workforce LA School-To-Work Youth Academy, 1990 November 5-1990 November 19 (Box 2057, Folder 7)
    Career and Continuing Education Report proposal that the District enter into a contract with the U.S. Department of Labor to develop and coordinate the Workforce LA School-To-Work Academy, a program combining academic and vocational experiences.
  - Work Permits, 1983 September 6 (Box 2057, Folder 8)
    Bulletin regarding Entertainment Work Permits for pupils and independent study requirements for credit and attendance purposes.
  - Work Stoppage, 1989 May 5-1989 June 7 (Box 2057, Folder 9)
    Memoranda and Inter-Office Correspondence on topics such as health benefits for striking employees, time-reporting instructions and questions and answers that may arise during work stoppages.
  - Year 2000 Steering Committee, 1997 December 1 (Box 2057, Folder 10)
    Copy of a Board Resolution that delegates authority to a Year 2000 Steering Committee to set project direction, maintain project oversight and monitor progress for Year 2000 compliance, the District's top systems and programming priority.
  - YMCA, 2007 October 23 (Box 2057, Folder 11)
    Board of Education Report from the Facilities Division which proposes that the Board authorize District staff to execute a Joint Use Lease Agreement with the YMCA of Metropolitan Los Angeles for the development of mutually beneficial facilities on the University High School campus.
  - Youth Activities, 1935-1983 (Box 2058)
    Excerpts of letters and a program from the District's Cavalcade of Youth program at the Hollywood Bowl and Bulletins on Defense Training Programs for National Youth Administration (N.Y.A.).
    Materials also include Youth Services Program calendars, brochures and reports, correspondence, proposal and brochure for Sugar Ray Robinson's Youth Foundation, Advantages of Youth Services booklet and summary sheets for Groups Using Board of Education Athletic and Recreational Facilities on a Permit Basis.
  - Youth Centers, 2007 October 23 (Box 2059, Folder 1)
    Facilities Services Division Board of Education Report proposal regarding the establishment of a Youth Center to facilitate after-school, evening and weekend services to "at risk" youth at Markham Middle School.
  - Youth Education, 1949 August 5-1959 July 17 (Box 2059, Folder 2)
    Emergency Communication to the Committee of the Whole from Superintendent Stoddard regarding the establishment of a Youth Education Clinic at the Custer Avenue School to provide remedial services for junior and senior high school boys who require special services due to attendance issues and other "maladjustments" with school and community.
  - Youth Opportunities Unlimited, 1993 July 19 (Box 2059, Folder 3)
    Committee of the Whole Report concerning the establishment of alternative high school, Youth Opportunities Unlimited (YOU).
  - Youth Suicide Prevention Program, 1983-1991 (Box 2059, Folder 4)
    Bulletins, Committee Communications and Suicide Prevention Unit Updates concerning the District's Youth Suicide Prevention Program.
  - Zoning, 1927-2001 (Box 2059, Folder 5-8)
    Correspondence, Committee Reports and maps pertaining to city and county zoning ordinances and rezoning of District land and school sites.
    Materials include an Official Atlas District Zoning Map of the City of Los Angeles as authorized by City Council and correspondence opposing the location of a mental hospital on Sepulveda Boulevard near Van Nuys High School.
- Personnel, 1921-2000
  The personnel records include documents generated by the Board and the Personnel Division that concern certificated and classified employees. Certificated employees are those for whom state educational credentials are prescribed by law. Classified employees are those for whom no definite educational credentials are required. Materials include copies of Board minutes, standing committee reports and correspondence pertaining to matters such as staff integration, salary, investigations, grievance procedures, reduction in force, employee organizations and collective bargaining.
  - Certificated, 1921-2000
    - Absence, 1935-1973 (Box 2199, Folder 1, Box 2149)
      Personnel Division Memoranda and Controlling Division Bulletins pertaining to policies for involuntary and excused absences.
      Box 2,149: (1935-1962).
      Box 2,199: (1969-1973).
    - Adjustment Procedures, 1947 February 24-1985 June 17 (Box 2199, Folder 4-5, Box 2119, Folder 3-4)
      Correspondence and excerpts from Minutes concerning grievances, transfers, reduction in force and Board Rules related to adjustment procedures involving plans for the adjustment of personal and professional problems.
      Box 2,119: (1947-1970).
      Box 2,199: (1971-1985).
    - Administrators, 1954 May 28-1996 July 15 (Box 2190, Folder 1-2, Box 2200, Folder 1, Box 2119, Folder 5, Box 2120, Box 2212, Folder 5-6)
      Board Rules and policies related to the selection process, criteria and qualifications for administrative positions.
      Box 2,119-2,120: (1954-1971).
      Box 2,190: (1971-1979).
      Box 2,200: (1980-1996).
      Box 2,212: (1977-1989).
    - Adult Education, 1939 May 15-1982 August 2 (Box 2199, Folder 2-3)
      Personnel Division Communications concerning Adult Education teachers.
    - Advisers, 1965 July 18-1992 April 20 (Box 2200, Folder 2-6)
      Standing Committee Reports and Communications concerning Adviser positions.
    - Affirmative Action, 1974 February 28-1976 December 9 (Box 2200, Folder 7)
      Correspondence from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), Watts Branch concerning the District's Publication #354 Racial and Ethnic Survey, Fall 1975 which it considered in violation of the 1964 Civil Rights Act and its amendment of 1972. The NAACP recommended that the District adopt an affirmative action policy to balance employment between the ethnic minority and majority personnel. Materials also include a Superintendent's Communication presented to the Committee of the While regarding the proposed adoption of the attached Equal Opportunity Policy and Affirmative Action Program and correspondence of commendation from Women Educators (WE).
    - Age Limits, 1979 January 15-1986 June 23 (Box 2206, Folder 6)
      Personnel and Schools Committee Communications concerning Board Rules regarding employment age and continuance of employment.
    - Assignments, 1934 July 19-2000 June 13 (Box 2120, Folder 5-6, Box 2121, Folder 1-4, Box 2201, Box 2150)
      Assignment policies and rules regarding the election, promotion and placement of employees such as principals, vice-principals, secondary teachers and junior college instructors.
      Box 2,120-2,121: (1934-1972).
      Box 2,150: (1939-1975).
      Box 2,201: (1934-2000).
    - Board Permit, 1989 August 11 (Box 2202, Folder 4)
      Board Bulletin regarding the application and renewal of Board Permits which are granted by the Board to authorize teachers to teach subjects not included as part of their regular credential.
    - Career Increment, 1981 August 10-1981 August 24 (Box 2202, Folder 5)
      Personnel and Schools Committee Report approving new Board Rule 4725, Establishment of Career Increment. Report includes this Board Rule as an attachment.
    - Citizenship, 1935 July 31-1970 June 4 (Box 2206, Folder 7)
      Law and Rules Committee Communications updating Administrative Guide section which includes Citizenship of Certificated Employees.
    - Classification, 1939 May 15-1998 January 7 (Box 2121, Folder 5-6, Box 2202, Folder 6-7, Box 2188, Box 2151, Box 2152, Folder 1-3, Box 2122, Box 2123)
      Personnel Division and Standing Committee Reports and Communications concerning the classification and reclassification of certificated personnel.
      Box 2,121-2,123: (1939-1976).
      Box 2,151: (1976-1980).
      Box 2,152: (1980-1983).
      Box 2,188: (1983-1989).
      Box 2,202: (1989-1998).
    - Coaches, 1999 February 9-1999 February 23 (Box 2202, Folder 8)
      Budget Services and Financial Planning Division Communication concerning District matching funds for Assembly Bill (AB) 2741 - Coaching Education.
    - Code, 1939 May 4-1961 July 3 (Box 2202, Folder 9)
      Bulletins concerning new position class codes and Standing Committee Communications pertaining to modifications to assignment code bases. Assignment bases describe the different working periods during the year required for the performance of District work.
    - Code of Ethics, 1954-1962 (Box 2202, Folder 10)
      Copies of the National Education Association's Proposed Basic Code of Ethics for the Education Profession, Code of Ethics for Government Service and Tentative Code of Ethics for the Association of Elementary School Administrators of Los Angeles.
    - Collective Bargaining, 1989-1995 (Box 2203, Folder 1)
      Board of Education Reports concerning Memorandum of Understanding between the District and Associated Administrators of Los Angeles (AALA) and Policy Position Related to the District's Organizational Security Arrangement Proposal to United Teachers Los Angeles (UTLA).
    - Committee on Assignments, 1989 September 11 (Box 2203, Folder 2)
      Personnel Division Bulletin concerning Committee on Assignments Authorization which provides additional instructional options and increases the flexibility in the assignment of teachers to meet either instructional needs or to enrich the instructional program.
    - C.P.R. Committee, 1921-1950 (Box 2124, Folder 1)
      Reports and correspondence concerning the Compensation, Policies and Regulations (C.P.R.) Committee for certificated personnel.
    - Consultants, 1945 October 22-1989 August 3 (Box 2203, Folder 3-4)
      Standing Committee Reports and Communications concerning consultant services.
    - Contracts, 1946 May13-1996 December 16 (Box 2203, Folder 5-6)
      Correspondence, petitions and Board Rules concerning teacher contracts.
    - Coordinators, 1953 August 24-1996 October 21 (Box 2148, Folder 1-3, Box 2203, Folder 7-11, Box 2190, Folder 3-4, Box 2199, Folder 6)
      Personnel Division Communications prepared for the Personnel and Schools Committee concerning approval on personnel action for Coordinator positions and Statements of Duties for various Coordinator positions.
      Box 2,148: (1953-1978).
      Box 2,190: (1979-1984).
      Box 2,199: (1977-1989).
      Box 2,203: (1984-1996).
    - Counselors, 1958 June 23-1992 March 9 (Box 2154, Folder 3, Box 2124, Folder 2-3, Box 2204, Folder 1, Box 2191, Folder 1-2, Box 2152, Folder 3-4, Box 2153, Folder 1-3)
      Box 2,124: Committee Communications and Board Rules concerning counselor positions (1959-1974).
      Box 2,152: Correspondence concerning the noon-duty aide program, Committee on Research Studies Non Duty-Aides Program Report and copies of the Los Angeles Elementary Teachers Club Board Presentation on Noon Time Activities (1958-1969).
      Box 2,153 and 2,191: Personnel Division Communications recommending that actions be approved for counselor positions and Bulletins and Board Minutes describing the selection, assignment and responsibilities of counselors (1960-1985).
      Box 2,154: Materials include the Personnel and Schools Committee Report which established the Counselor Aide Class and Committee Reports and Communications concerning the Counselor Aide Program (1973-1977).
      Box 2,204: Committee of the Whole Reports concerning the election of counselors (1986-1992).
    - Credentials, 1934 October 18-2000 July 25 (Box 2192, Box 2204, Folder 2-4)
      Administrative Guide Rules concerning county certificates, teaching credential requirements and specializations. Materials include eligibility lists of certificated employees available for assignments, proposals for credential waiver authorizations and reports of teacher assignments and credential authorizations.
      Box 2,192: (1934-1986).
      Box 2,204: (1972-2000).
    - Deans, 1972 August 24-1990 September 10 (Box 2153, Folder 4-5, Box 2204, Folder 5-6)
      Communications prepared by the Personnel Division pertaining to approvals of Dean position elections at various school sites.
      Box 2,153: (1972-1980).
      Box 2,204: (1980-1990).
    - Degree Requirement, 1953 September 22-1975 October 23 (Box 2124, Folder 5, Box 2205, Folder 1-2)
      Box 2,124: Correspondence of protest against the Board's new salary schedule which requires advanced degrees in order to attain the maximum teaching salary (1953-1954).
      Box 2,205: Board Rules and Personnel Division Communications concerning degree requirements for certificated positions (1953-1975).
    - Demotions, 1972 February 24-1991 June 24 (Box 2205, Folder 3)
      Committee of the Whole Reports authorizing demotions, and excerpts from Board Minutes concerning Closed Session demotion actions.
    - Department Heads, 1936 August 12-1983 October 27 (Box 2124, Folder 4, Box 2205)
      Box 2,124: Correspondence and excerpts from Minutes concerning the responsibility for the appointment of Department Chairmen at secondary schools (1936-1969).
      Box 2,205: Suggested Responsibilities of Department Chairpersons Bulletin (1983).
    - Differentials, 1980 September 9-1992 March 6 (Box 2205, Folder 5)
      Bulletins and Standing Committee Communications concerning salary differentials.
    - Directors & Presidents, 1946 June 27-1991 September 4 (Box 2154, Folder 1-2, Box 2205, Folder 6)
      Box 2,154: Communications prepared by the Personnel Division pertaining to approvals of Director position elections at various school sites and Committee Reports concerning College Presidents (1946-1983).
      Box 2,205: Communications prepared by the Personnel Division pertaining to approvals of Director position elections (1983-1991).
    - Dismissals, 1934-1999 (Box 2191, Folder 3-5, Box 2205, Folder 7, Box 2115, Box 2116, Box 2117)
      Board correspondence to employees concerning dismissals of certificated personnel at high schools and junior colleges for reasons such as reduction in enrollment, a male teacher impersonating a woman and "conditions beyond its control."
      Materials include signed protest correspondence.
      Box 2,115-2,117: (1934-1947).
      Box 2,191: (1935-1985).
      Box 2,205: (1985-1999).
    - Elementary Administrator Development Program, 1964 September 1-1964 September 21 (Box 2120, Folder 3)
      A description of the Elementary School Administrator Development Program and copies of applications for this professional development training program.
    - Eligible List, 1985 August 19-1990 June 15 (Box 2206, Folder 1)
      Copies of unranked eligible lists of certificated employees.
    - Emergency Permits, 1996 August 5-1996 August 19 (Box 2206, Folder 2)
      Personnel Division Communication proposal for Declaration of Need for Fully Qualified Educators in order to utilize emergency teaching and services permits.
    - Emergency Teachers, 1996 August 5-1996 August 19 (Box 2206, Folder 3)
      Personnel Division Communication proposal to request a waiver to exceed the 5% of emergency licensed teachers in any school.
    - Employee Organizations, 1946-1982 (Box 2172, Box 2173, Box 2174, Box 2175)
      Box 2,172: Employee Relations Council Operating Guide, correspondence from Los Angeles Teachers Association (LATA) and Affiliated Teacher Organizations of Los Angeles (ATOLA), LATA Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws, lists of certificated employee organizations and The Crisis in Elementary Education: An Introduction to a Master Plan for Education by the Association of Elementary School Administrators (1946-1967).
      Box 2,173: Correspondence related organizational records from the Council of Administrators and Supervisors of Los Angeles (CASLA), Professional Educators Los Angeles (PELA), Association of Classroom Teachers Los Angeles (ACT-LA), Secondary Teachers Organization of Los Angeles, Inc. (SeTO), Los Angeles Association of Secondary School Administrators (LASSA) and the California School Employees Association (CSEA) representing Unit A: Security (1962-1982).
      Box 2,174: Summary of Joint Recommendations Los Angeles City Schools and The Certificated Employee Council, Special Reports from the Office of Staff Relations, correspondence from the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), Local 1021 and Negotiating Proposals of the Certificated Employee Council (1969-1976).
      Box 2,175: Unified Negotiating Council and Certificated Employee Council Membership Audits (1966-1976).
    - Employees' Personal Property, 1974 June 13-1974 June 17 (Box 2206, Folder 4)
      Committee of the Whole Report regarding changes to Board Rule 1672, Replacement or Repair of Employees' Personal Property.
    - Employment, 1936 March 30-1992 April 22 (Box 2156, Box 2206, Folder 5, Box 2131)
      Box 2,131: Inter-Office Correspondence concerning reduction in force of certificated employees, policies and procedures, chart of types of classes and teachers, transcripts of grievance hearings and correspondence of protest and approval regarding the recommended demotion of Dr. Edwin Baldwin Angier, Director of the Clarence W. Pierce School of Agriculture (1939-1972).
      Box 2,156: Materials include applications for positions, Personnel Division Communications concerning age limits, court cases involving the Dilworth Act, Board Rules requiring loyalty questions and the oath of allegiance and Teachers and Schools Committee Reports on residence requirements (1936-1978).
      Box 2,206: Personnel and Schools Committee Communication regarding revisions to the District's Affirmative Action Program and Equal Opportunity Policy and Committee of the Whole Communications concerning Board Rule revisions (1972-1992).
    - Evaluations, 1981 April 1-1990 November 2 (Box 2206, Folder 8)
      Bulletins regarding Guidelines for Stull Evaluation of Certificated Personnel.
    - Examinations, 1936 January 8-1995 January 23 (Box 2133, Folder 1-3, Box 2206, Folder 9-12, Box 2207)
      Box 2,133: Committee Communications and Board Rules, policies and procedures concerning examination procedures for employees seeking promotion. Materials also include records for individual cases (1936-1968).
      Box 2,206: Transcripts of wire recordings of Board meeting discussions of teacher examination procedures and copies of Board Resolutions and Standing Committee Communications concerning examination procedures (1953-1995).
      Box 2,207: Personnel Division Communications concerning fees, fingerprints, photographs and experience portions of teacher examinations (1936-1972).
    - Fringe Benefits, 1967 May 15-1997 June 2 (Box 2207, Folder 4)
      Standing Committee Communications and correspondence concerning fringe benefits for teachers.
    - Grievance Procedure, 1984 November 9-1991 November 4 (Box 2207, Folder 5)
      Committee of the Whole Report and Bulletin concerning grievance procedures.
    - Hardship Appeal, 1977 May 26-1977 June 20 (Box 2207, Folder 6)
      Committee of the Whole Report with attached Teacher Integration Program. This Program includes a hardship appeal procedure for teachers who wish to file a written declaration of hardship to request exemption from a mandatory transfer.
    - Health Exams, 1935 August 7-1983 April 25 (Box 2207, Folder 7, Box 2193, Folder 1-2)
      Personnel and Schools Committee Reports and Board Rules concerning health standards and physician exams regarding approval of applicants for District employment and Bulletins concerning students and employees with AIDS/HIV infection.
    - Hillman's Proposed Reorganization, 1953-1971 (Box 2148, Folder 8)
      Materials include a transcript of a wire recording from the Committee of the Whole meeting presentation by Mr. Hillman on his proposed reorganization of the District's administration, Survey Proposal of the District's Organization and Management, Organization Charts, Report of Certificated Salary Survey and a copy of a salary schedule survey which compares maximum salaries of administration positions in twenty large California school districts.
    - Holiday, 1979 October 15-1991 September 4 (Box 2207, Folder 8)
      Board Rules and Memoranda regarding holidays.
    - Hours, 1937-1990 (Box 2207, Folder 9-10)
      Committee Reports and Memoranda pertaining to work hours, assignments and time off.
    - Informals and Wire Recordings, 1952 September 25-1953 September 24 (Box 2120, Folder 4)
      Tentative Communication to Committee of the Whole regarding Elementary Teacher Recruitment and Selection Policies, Personnel Division correspondence related to the dismissal of probationary certificated employees, Inter-Office correspondence on policies and practices relative to the probationary period for new teachers and adjustment procedures and transcripts of wire recordings from Board meetings and Committee of the Whole meeting notes concerning grievance procedures.
    - In-Service Training, 1979-1992 (Box 2208, Folder 1-4)
      Districtwide In-Service Education Classes catalogs and Committee of the Whole Communications concerning agreements for in-service training programs.
    - Institute, 1936-1972 (Box 2132, Box 2133, Folder 4-5)
      Box 2,132: Bulletins, announcements and Committee Communications concerning the Institute for Certificated Personnel, an annual professional development program for teachers.
      Box 2,133: Protest correspondence concerning the discontinuance of the Teachers' Institute and the addition of five days to the school year. Memos, Committee Reports and transcripts of Board Minutes concerning the finality of these decisions by Board action.
    - Internship, 1968 January 20-1994 June 20 (Box 2207, Folder 12)
      Standing Committee Communications and District correspondence concerning the District Internship Program for teacher training, Administrative Interns and UCLA Interns.
    - Investigations, 1953 May 7-1987 March 30 (Box 2157, Box 2193, Folder 3-4)
      Box 2,157: Case files on individual employees which include the following: legal action against the Board on behalf of an employee alleging racial discrimination, charge for dismissal of an employee for striking her pupils over the course of three years at Berendo, Gage and Stevenson Junior High Schools and settlement of claim for back salary and benefits for a secondary teacher suspended and given notice of dismissal for violation of the Levering and Dilworth Acts (1953-1975).
      Box 2,193: Investigations of certificated employees and Personnel and Schools Committee Communications concerning dismissals. Materials include a copy of Claim of Abraham Minkus vs. Los Angeles Board of Education and Claim of Serril Gerber vs. Los Angeles Board of Education, tenured teachers who were fired by the Board as a result of the House Un-American Activities Committee hearings. Materials also include a full page advertisement in favor of Sal Castro, "The Brown Socrates" remaining at Lincoln High School (1968-1987).
    - Ladder, 1996 October 7 (Box 2208, Folder 5)
      The Ladder: Information For and About Paraeducators Pursuing Teaching Degrees newsletter.
    - Layoffs, 1975 June 12-1982 May 24 (Box 2208, Folder 6)
      Committee of the Whole Reports and correspondence concerning certificated personnel layoffs.
    - Leave of Absence, 1930 January 6-1999 June 3 (Box 2154, Folder 4-5, Box 2162, Box 2155, Box 2197, Folder 1-2, Box 2118, Box 2134, Box 2268, Box 2208, Folder 7-10, Box 2209, Folder 1-11)
      Leave of Absence request forms, correspondence, reports and Board Rules related to sabbatical, illness, acts of violence, family care, jury duty, maternity and military service.
      Box 2,118: (1936-1966).
      Box 2,134: (1932-1971).
      Box 2,154: (1942-1975).